Guide to the Louis Justement papers, 1946-1968 MS2045
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Louis Justement papers
1946-1968
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Justement, Louis
MS2045
1.5 Linear Feet
Collection consists of correspondence, newspaper and periodical articles, patents, meeting minutes, reports, programs, and press releases. The material dates from 1946-68. The correspondence comes from the Committee on Urban Planning of the American Institute of Architects and the Interprofessional Urban Planning Committee, which Justement chaired from 1946-49.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Biographical Note
Louis Justement (1891-1968) practiced architecture in Washington D.C. from 1919 through 1968. He received his bachelor's degree in architecture from George Washington University in 1911 and opened his own architecture firm in 1924.
He served three terms as president of the Washington Chapter of the American Institute of Architects, Middle Atlantic District. He served as chairman of the A.I.A. Committee on Urban Planning from 1946 though 1949. He was considered an authority on private and public large-scale housing projects and some of his well-known projects located in Washington include Sibley Memorial Hospital, U.S. Courthouse, Howard University Medical School, and the Meridian Hill Hotel. He supported the development of rapid transit for the metropolitan area and worked on the drafting of the original plans for the redevelopment of Southwest Washington.
He was born in New York City and died at Sibley Memorial Hospital in 1968.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, newspaper and periodical articles, patents, meeting minutes, reports, programs, and press releases. The material dates from 1946-68. The correspondence comes from the Committee on Urban Planning of the American Institute of Architects and the Interprofessional Urban Planning Committee, which Justement chaired from 1946-49. The correspondence of both committees deals with the postwar housing situation, proposals for legislation, programs for urban redevelopment, and meeting minutes. The collection also includes correspondence relating to the Urban Renewal Council of Washington D.C. The Council was a group of citizens appointed to advise and assist the Commissioners of the District of Columbia. Justement was appointed in 1959 for a two-year term. The material for the Committee on Urban Planning has statements from Justement and other people about various topics such as housing issues, zoning, and building codes. These statements were presented to Congressional committees and professional architecture organizations.
Collection Organization
Organized into seven series: Biographical information, American Institute of Architects Committee on Urban Planning, Interprofessional Urban Planning Committee, Manuscript, Patents, Periodicals and newspaper articles, and Urban Renewal Council.
Washington (D.C.); Architects; Urban renewal; Housing; Urban Renewal Council of Washington, D.C.; Justement, Louis; Interprofessional Urban Planning Committee; American Institute of Architects. Urban Planning and Design Committee
- Biographical information, undated; MS2045 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of biographical information for Louis Justement.
  - Biographical Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Institute of Architects, Committee on Urban Planning, 1946-1949; MS2045 Series 2; 0.75 Linear feet
  This series consists of correspondence, minutes, newsletters, programs, reports, statements, legislative bills, and news releases related to Justement's work with the Committee on Urban Planning for the American Institute of Architects. The material dates from 1946-49.
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1947 January-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    General note
    Selected items from this folder are described below. Please note that this is not a comprehensive list of materials within this folder.
    - Correspondence: Louis Justement and Earl T. Heitschmidt, 1947 January 30; Item 1
    - Correspondence: Edmund B. Purves and Philip B. Fleming, 1947 February 07; Item 2
    - Correspondence: Louis Justement and Edmund B. Purves, 1947 March 20; Item 3
  - Correspondence, 1947 June-September (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Selected items from this folder are described below. Please note that this is not a comprehensive list of material within this folder.
    - Statement on Housing Policy for the A.I.A. -- Henry S. Churchill, 1947 June 14; Item 1
  - Correspondence, 1947 October-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Albert J. Evers and Louis Justement, 1947 November 03; Item 1
  - Correspondence, 1948 January-July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1948 August-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949 January-1950 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Douglas William Orr and George Cannon Young, 1949 January 19; Item 1
  - Bills (Legislation), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes and Memos Atomic Age Architecture Committee, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters (various organizations), 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - News Releases, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs and Reports, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Statements, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subject: Housing, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subject: Urban Slum, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Interprofessional Urban Planning Committee, 1946-1949; MS2045 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of correspondence related to Justement's work with the Interprofessional Urban Planning Committee. The material dates from 1946-49.
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1947 January-1949 January (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948 March-1949 January (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Manuscript, undated; MS2045 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series has a manuscript for the book "The Challenge of the City."
  - "The Challenge of the City", undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Patents, undated; MS2045 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains correspondence and patents. The correspondence is dated 1926.
  - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Commissioner of Patents, undated; Item 1
  - Patents, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Commissioner of Patents and Louis Justement, 1926 October 07 (Box 3, Folder 5 item 1)
- Periodical and newspaper articles, 1946-1968; MS2045 Series 6; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains newspaper and periodical articles and scrapbooks. The material is dated 1946-68.
  - Newspaper Articles, 1946-1952 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Periodical Articles, 1946-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Urban Renewal Council, 1958-1960; MS2045 Series 7; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains correspondence related to Justement's work with the Urban Renewal Council. The material is dated from 1958-60.
  - Urban Renewal Council, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Proposal for Service to Displaced Families, 1959 December 30; Item 1